A Finding Aid to the Dorothy Dehner Papers, 1920-1987 (bulk 1951-1987), in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Dorothy Dehner papers
1920-1987
bulk 1951-1987
Archives of American Art
Dehner, Dorothy, 1901-1994
AAA.dehndoro
Archival Resource Key
4 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor Dorothy Dehner measure 4 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1987, with the bulk of the material dating from 1951 to 1987. The collection documents Dehner's life, work, and professional and personal relationships, with particular focus on her mid-to-late career. Papers include extensive correspondence, business and financial papers, sound recordings and transcripts of interviews, writings by Dehner and others, printed material documenting Dehner's career, scattered photographs, two etchings, and scattered personal papers and material relating to David Smith.
Biographical Note
Dorothy Dehner was an abstract sculptor of the New York school who was also an accomplished painter, printmaker, author, and educator.
Dehner was born in Cleveland, Ohio in 1901. Her father died when she was about ten and the family moved to Pasadena, California in 1915. After the death of her mother and sister, she was raised by her mother's sister, Aunt Florence. Dehner was exposed to art as a child, receiving instruction in drawing and painting. She studied drama for a year at UCLA in 1922-1923 before moving to New York with the intention of pursuing a theatrical career. In 1925, she traveled alone to Europe, where she visited Italy, Switzerland, and France and where she began to draw seriously.
Upon her return to New York, Dehner enrolled in the Art Students League intending to study sculpture, but, uninspired by the work of William Zorach's sculpture class, ended up studying drawing with Kimon Nicolaides instead. In 1926, she met fellow artist David Smith in the rooming house they shared. At her suggestion, he too enrolled in the Art Students League. In 1927, they were married.
At the League, Dehner and Smith studied with the modernist painter, Jan Matulka, and befriended Weber and Thomas Furlong, through whom they met the Russian painter and theoretician, John Graham. Graham introduced them to the avant-garde art world and had a profound influence on Dehner and Smith and their work. Other young artists they befriended at this time included Adolph Gottlieb, Mark Rothko, and Edgar and Lucille Corcos Levy. In 1929, after a visit to the Furlong's summer home in upstate New York, Dehner and Smith bought a farm in Bolton Landing, which became their permanent home in 1940 and was later named Terminal Iron Works. They spent eight months in the Virgin Islands, in 1931-1932, where Dehner painted abstract still lifes of shells and marine life. In the fall of 1935, they traveled to Europe, where they met up with Graham in Paris, spent five months in Greece, and toured the Soviet Union, with other stops along the way.
During her years at Bolton Landing (from 1940 to 1950), Dehner progressed in her work, producing a series of paintings titled Life on the Farm and embarking upon a series of abstract geometric drawings in ink and watercolor. In 1943, she had a joint exhibition with Smith at the Albany Institute of History and Art. Three years later, she participated in the annual exhibition of Audubon Artists and was awarded a first prize for drawing, and in 1948, she had her first one-woman show at Skidmore College.
Dehner left Bolton Landing in 1950 (she was divorced from Smith two years later) and returned to school, earning her degree from Skidmore College in 1952. She moved back to New York City, and supported herself over the next several years by teaching at various schools, including the Barnard School for Girls. She had her first solo exhibition in the city at the Rose Fried Gallery in 1952, and studied engraving at Stanley William Hayter's Atelier 17. At this point, Dehner started making sculpture, first experimenting in wax and then casting her wax sculptures in bronze. In 1955, she began working at the Sculpture Center, and from this point on, focused mainly on sculpture with occasional forays in drawing and printmaking. In addition to works in bronze, she went on to create sculptures in wood (during the 1970s) and steel (during the 1980s).
In 1955, Dehner married the New York publisher, Ferdinand Mann. That same year, she joined the Willard Gallery, run by Marian Willard. She had her first exhibition of drawings there in 1955 (which led to a solo exhibition at the Art Institute of Chicago) and her first sculpture show there in 1957. Dehner continued to show at the Willard Gallery regularly until 1976. Over the next several decades, Dehner's work was frequently exhibited in solo and groups exhibitions at museums and galleries across the country, and was acquired for both public and private collections.
In addition to her art work, Dehner was also a published poet and writer. She wrote the foreword to the 1971 re-issue of John Graham's System and Dialectics of Art, and an essay on David Smith's "Medals for Dishonor," which was published in Art Journal in 1977. Two of her poems, "Past Tense" and "Two Lines," appeared in the journal Tracks in 1977.
Dehner continued to work into her nineties, and passed away in 1994.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of sculptor Dorothy Dehner measure 4 linear feet and date from 1920 to 1987, with the bulk of the material dating from 1951 to 1987. The collection documents Dehner's life, work, and professional and personal relationships, with particular focus on her mid-to-late career. Papers include extensive correspondence, business and financial papers, sound recordings and transcripts of interviews, writings by Dehner and others, printed material documenting Dehner's career, scattered photographs, two etchings, and scattered personal papers and material relating to David Smith.
Comprising a series of biographical material are personal papers such as notes on Dehner's biography and career, a list of things taken from Bolton Landing, and material relating to David Smith including a copy of his last will and testament, a letter of introduction (dating from their trip to Europe in the mid-1930s), and a chronology of Smith's life.
Correspondence consists of numerous letters and enclosures concerning both professional and personal matters. Correspondents include artists, museums, galleries, art dealers, researchers, curators, friends, and relatives. Correspondence documents Dehner's various personal and professional relationships, the active role she played in promoting and exhibiting her art work, as well as the key role she played in fostering art historical research on David Smith, herself, and other artists of her era, and her many other creative activities, including her various writing efforts.
Interviews include sound recordings of four interviews with Dehner, and a recording of an interview conducted with her for a documentary on David Smith. Also found is a transcription of an interview for which there is no recording.
Writings shed light on other aspects of Dehner's creativity and concerns. Dehner's writings include poems, such as one dated from high school and drafts of poems published in Tracks); and various pieces on John Graham. These include versions of a memoir, which were published as a foreword to the re-issue of System and Dialectics of Art, and as an article in Leonardo). Also found are writings on David Smith, including articles recalling Dehner's first meeting with him, and on Smith's 1940 work "Medals for Dishonor;" lectures and speeches; and various writings on art and other topics. Writings by others include essays on Dehner by Joan Marter and Judith McCandless.
Dehner's business and financial records document transactions with various galleries and art organizations and include records of loans, exhibitions, and sales through files for the Parsons-Dreyfuss Gallery, Philadelphia Art Alliance, Willard Gallery, and others. The series also includes scattered records relating to personal business matters and finances, such as Dehner's lists of artwork loaned, exhibited, and sold, receipts, tax records, and exhibition visitor books.
Printed material includes exhibition catalogs and announcements for Dehner's group and solo shows, and clippings on Dehner and a few other artists including David Smith. Artwork consists of two etchings, and photographs include photographs of Dehner, her second husband Ferdinand Mann, John Graham, and various works of art. Also found is an abstract photograph by David Smith, dating from circa 1934.
Arrangement
The Dorothy Dehner papers are arranged into 8 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1935-1982 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1927-1987 (Boxes 1-3; 2.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Interviews and Transcripts, 1963-1981 (Boxes 3-4; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, 1920-1987 (Box 3; 0.25 linear feet)
Series 5: Business and Financial Records, 1940-1987 (Box 3; 0.25 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1940-1987 (Boxes 3, 5; OV 6; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 7: Art Work, circa 1930s-circa 1960s (Box 5, OV 6; 0.05 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, 1930s-1986 (Box 5; 0.15 linear feet)
Related Material
Other resources in the Archives relating to Dorothy Dehner include oral history interviews with Dehner, October 1965 and December 1966, and a photograph of Dehner by Dena, 1966.
Separated Material
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of material lent for microfilming on reels D298 (portions), D298A, 1269 (portions) and 1372, including photographs of Dorothy Dehner and David Smith, sketchbooks, correspondence between Dehner and Smith, an inventory, and some printed material. Loaned materials were returned to the lender after filming and are not described in the collection Container Listing.
Provenance
The Dorothy Dehner papers were donated from 1967-1987 in increments by Dorothy Dehner. Dehner also loaned material for microfilming between 1967 and 1977, some of which was subsequently donated. The art work in the collection most likely belonged to Garnett McCoy originally, and was included in the collection during processing in 2005.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2023 and is available on the Archives of American Art website. Items not digitized include duplicates, blank versos of photographs, and some printed material such as the full text of publications of which only covers, title pages, and relevant pages have been digitized.
Sound recordings; Interviews; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Women artists; Women sculptors; Sketchbooks; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Authors -- New York (State) -- New York; Printmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Women printmakers; Women authors; Philadelphia Art Alliance; Willard Gallery; Smith, David, 1906-1965; Graham, John, 1887-1961; Matulka, Jan, 1890-1972
- Biographical Material, 1935-1982; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of scattered material shedding light on different aspects of Dehner's life and work. Included are various notes and lists created by Dehner consisting of information pertaining to her biography and career; a list of things that Dehner took with her when she left Bolton's Landing in 1951-1952; copies of selected clippings and typescript copies featuring press comments on Dehner's work in the mid-to late-1960s; proofs and copies of her biographical sketch in the publication, Who's Who; a photocopy of the honorary degree she received from Skidmore College; and a wedding announcement for her stepdaughter, Abby Mann Thernstrom.
  Also found here is some material relating to David Smith, including a chronology submitted for Dehner's review and bearing her editing marks, a copy of Smith's last will and testament, a letter of introduction for Smith from Audrey McMahon of the College Art Association (dating from their trip to Europe in the mid-1930s), a name tag for Smith of unknown origin, and 3 photocopied reproductions of artwork by Smith.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Series has been digitized in entirety.
  - Biographical and Career Information, circa 1950s-circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical and Career Information, 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Honorary Degree (photocopy), Skidmore College, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - List of Items Taken from Bolton Landing, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Press Comments on Dehner's Work, 1965-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Who's Who Entries, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - David Smith Material, 1935-circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Wedding Announcement for Abby Mann, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1927-1987; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 2.2 Linear feet
  Series consists of Dehner's personal and professional correspondence, comprised of mostly incoming letters but also some early drafts or copies of outgoing letters in addition to some enclosures such as loan agreements, shipping receipts, manuscripts, and printed material. Correspondents include museums, galleries, art dealers, curators, scholars, students, artists, writers, friends, and relatives. Correspondence largely documents Dehner's various personal and professional relationships, her efforts to promote and exhibit her artwork and to facilitate art historical research (on David Smith, herself, and other artists), and her various creative activities.
  Personal correspondents include David Smith, Smith's sister, Catherine, and his mother, Golda; Smith's second wife, Jean Smith Pond, and his two daughters, Rebecca and Candida; Dehner's second husband, Ferdinand Mann and stepdaughter, Abby (Mann) Thernstrom; friends and fellow artists, Edgar and Lucille Corcos Levy, Herman Cherry, and Louise Nevelson; and her heart surgeon, Elliott Hurwitt, among others. Dehner often established friendships with individuals who started out corresponding on a professional basis (such as curators, dealers, and students), so personal correspondence can often be found interspersed with professional correspondence.
  Professional correspondence typically relates to the loan, exhibition, and sale of Dehner's work and the Smith work that Dehner owned. Notable exhibitions documented include the 1950s traveling show of her watercolors and drawings, and group and solo shows including at the Philadelphia Art Alliance, Storm King Art Center, and Zimmerli Art Museum at Rutgers University. Also documented are Dehner's dealings with Mildred Constantine and Marian Willard (of the Willard Gallery), among others. Correspondence with curators, scholars, and students relates to research inquiries primarily about Smith, but also about Dehner herself and other artists of her era, such as John Graham, Irene Rice Pereira, and Louise Nevelson. Professional correspondence also concerns the editing and publication of the foreword she wrote for the re-issue of John Graham's System and Dialectics of Art, and the publication of her poems in the journal Tracks; certain matters pertaining to David Smith's estate, such as the disposition of some items belonging to Dehner and the controversial alteration of the painted surfaces of certain Smith sculptures carried out by executor Clement Greenberg; donations of art works to various institutions, including Dehner's effort to raise funds from Jan Matulka's former students to purchase and donate one of his paintings to the Guggenheim Museum; and the donation of her papers to the Archives of American Art, and subsequent permissions to access and publish from them.
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is typically arranged in alphabetical order according to name of correspondent. Some files contain the letters of various individuals and are arranged according to subject (e.g. "Various, Condolence Letters"). Letters from a correspondent with an unknown surname are arranged in a file according to first name, and unidentified letters and fragments are arranged in files at the end of the series. Related material can be found amongst business and financial papers.
  - A, General, circa 1946-circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - A. M. Sachs Gallery, 1980-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Abbeville Press, Inc., 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1960-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Archives of American Art, 1965-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Art for Offices, Ltd., circa 1970-circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Art Students League, 1975, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Artists for CORE, 1964-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Artists for Environment, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Asch, Maxine, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Associated American Artists, circa 1971-circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Audubon Artists, Inc., 1946, 1972, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - B, General, 1963-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - B. S. Livingston & Co., 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Barbara Fiedler Gallery, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bearor, Karen, 1984-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Benson Gallery, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bernice Steinbaum Gallery, 1985-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Biddle, George, circa 1960-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Blake, Elizabeth, 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Bloomington Normal Association, 1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - C, General, circa 1961-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Canyon Road Art Gallery, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Cherry, Herman, circa 1948-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Cherry, Herman, 1967-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cherry, Herman, circa 1974-1977, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Colin, Ralph, 1959-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Constantine, Mildred, circa 1940s-circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Constantine, Mildred, 1947-1948, 1967-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Crockwell, Margaret and Doug, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Cummer Gallery of Art, 1963-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - D, General, 1952-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Davidson, Maryetta, circa 1960s-circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Day, Holliday (Holly), circa 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Department of State (Art in Embassies Program), 1966-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Design Corner, circa 1973-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Discovery Art Galleries, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - E, General, 1946-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Editions Alecto Ltd., 1963-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Edmonton Art Gallery (Karen Wilkin), 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Elvehjem Art Center, University of Wisconsin, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - F, General, circa 1946-circa 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Includes Fried Gallery which represented Dehenr in the early 1950s before Willard Gallery
  - Fairweather-Hardin Gallery, 1960-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Fitch, Cleo and James, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Fogg Art Museum, Harvard University (Jane Cone), 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Fort Wayne Museum of Art, 1973-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - G, General, circa 1950-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Gallery Gemini, 1984-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - General Electric, 1983-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - George, Herbert (Tracks), 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Graham, Elinor, circa 1966-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Gray, Cleve, circa 1966-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Greenberg, Ben and Boris, 1979, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Gres Gallery, circa 1959-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Grey Art Gallery, New York University, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Guggenheim Museum, 1968-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - H, General, 1945-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Haggerty, Margaret, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Heller, William, circa 1966-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden, 1975-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Horak, Walter, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Hurwitt, Elliott, 1962-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Hyde Collection, 1973-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - I, General, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - J, General, 1965-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Johns Hopkins Press, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 74)
    Documents Dehner's foreword for Graham's book System and Dialectics of Art
  - Jones, Virginia, 1980-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Juster, Kathleen and Pete, circa 1960s-circa 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - K, General, circa 1967-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Kahn, Anita, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Kling Interior Design, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Krauss, Rosalind, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - L, General, circa 1966-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Laird, Susan, circa 1971-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Lawrence, Ellen, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Legett, [Priscilla] (Hyde Collection Curator), 1973-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Leonardo (Pergamon Press), 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 85)
    Includes documentation of Dehner's article about John Graham
  - Levy, David, circa 1975-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Levy, Edgar and Lucille, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Levy, Edgar and Lucille, 1943-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Levy, Edgar and Lucille, 1948-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Levy, Edgar and Lucille, 1950-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Levy, Edgar and Lucille, 1961-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Levy, Edgar and Lucille, Copies/Transcripts, 1935-1942; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Levy, Edgar and Lucille, Copies/Transcripts, 1943-1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Levy, Edgar and Lucille, Copies/Transcripts, 1946-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Levy, Joel, circa 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Lowe, Ira, 1965-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 96)